<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: referensi | 12" behind the camera]]></title>
  <link href="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/categories/referensi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-13T16:26:33+07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Endy Muhardin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Belajar Lighting]]></title>
    <link href="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/referensi/belajar-lighting/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T09:14:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/referensi/belajar-lighting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Enaknya belajar fotografi di jaman Youtube, segala macam tutorial ada. Saking banyaknya, kita kesulitan memilih mana yang bagus mana yang jelek. Mau ditonton semua, bisa-bisa menghabiskan masa remaja.</p>

<p>Untuk menghemat waktu kita semua, saya sudah mengumpulkan beberapa video di Youtube yang bagus cara penyampaiannya. Semoga bermanfaat.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Di video tutorial ini, para instruktur menggunakan berbagai teknologi dan perangkat lampu. Jangan pusing dengan alat yang belum kita miliki. Perhatikanlah hal-hal berikut:</p>

<ul>
<li>Penempatan posisi lampu terhadap subjek dan latar</li>
<li>Intensitas cahaya</li>
<li>Penggunaan modifier (payung, softbox, reflektor, gel, dsb)</li>
<li>Bagian subjek yang terang (highlight)</li>
<li>Posisi jatuhnya bayangan (shadow)</li>
<li>Transisi dari highlight ke shadow (fall-off)</li>
<li>Sifat bayangan, hard (tepi bayangan garisnya tegas) atau soft (tepi bayangan memiliki gradasi)</li>
<li>Warna cahaya</li>
</ul>


<h2>In Studio</h2>

<p>Pertama, kita mulai dulu dengan penggunaan satu lampu. Tutorial dari The Slanted Lens ini merupakan fundamental lighting untuk portrait. Di sini kita juga memahami tentang berbagai teknik dan istilah dasar seperti Rembrandt Light, Split Light, Broad Light, Short Light, Butterfly/Paramount Light, Loop Light. Di akhir video ada sedikit penjelasan menggunakan tiga lampu untuk key, fill, dan rim.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('gmmZECtP3oM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/gmmZECtP3oM?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/gmmZECtP3oM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gmmZECtP3oM" id="gmmZECtP3oM" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Portrait Lighting for Photography and Video!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Sign up at http://theslantedlens.com for free video lighting tutorials & gear giveaways ***

Portrait Lighting for Photography and Video
by Jay P. Morgan Photography

There are several lighting positions that photographers have developed over the years. People like George Hurrell, who used tungsten to shoot stars, used these lighting positions. Learn to identify what a butterfly or Rembrandt light is. Knowing these positions, and where the light placed to create them,  will help you see how photographers light their images. These are departure points from which you will create your own look and direction. Its hard to depart from someplace you have never been there. This will teach you the basics and give you a good foundation to build on. 

This video is not as slick as some of the others we have done but it has great basic instructions on portrait lighting. (Don't miss the ending its the most exciting part!)</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Untuk portrait, ada beberapa penggunaan cahaya, yaitu:</p>

<ul>
<li>key light : sumber cahaya utama yang menerangi subjek</li>
<li>fill light : sumber cahaya lemah untuk mengurangi (tapi tidak menghilangkan) bayangan agar tidak terlalu kontras</li>
<li>rim/separation light : cahaya untuk menerangi sisi (rim) subjek supaya tidak tercampur (separation) dengan latar</li>
<li>background/kicker light : cahaya untuk menerangi latar belakang supaya lebih joss</li>
</ul>


<p>Selanjutnya, tonton video berikut untuk memahami keempat fungsi cahaya tersebut.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('maM4dWbK0A0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/maM4dWbK0A0?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/maM4dWbK0A0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=maM4dWbK0A0" id="maM4dWbK0A0" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Photographic Lighting Made Simple! DSLR 3 Light Portrait Lesson Part One</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Sign up at http://theslantedlens.com for free video lighting tutorials & gear giveaways ***

Photographic Lighting Made Simple! DSLR 3 Light Portrait Lesson Part One
by Jay P. Morgan Photography

This is the first in an on going series of Videos that I will post showing how I light and create images. My goal is to not just show the behind the scenes of my work but to provide easy to follow instructions on how to create the lighting you see. No guessing or trying to figure it out. It is clear. 
This is s simple 3 light Portrait lesson that shows the basics of a 3 light set up to photograph a person.
Part 2 will show how I use special effects and a couple of more lights to push the shot a little farther.
This piece was edited by Adam Consolo.</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Setelah paham fungsi tersebut, kita bisa melanjutkan menonton video berikut. Intinya adalah, sumber cahaya tidak harus dari lampu, tapi bisa juga dari pantulan cahaya. Dengan bermodalkan satu lampu saja, hasilnya bisa sangat bervariasi. Tapi prinsip dasarnya tetap sama.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('F9gVQFhCXEQ');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/F9gVQFhCXEQ?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/F9gVQFhCXEQ/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F9gVQFhCXEQ" id="F9gVQFhCXEQ" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Advanced One Light Setups - Photography & Video Tutorial</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Win a Spider Holster Pro Single Camera System: http://theslantedlens.com/2013/spider...

From Jay P. Morgan,

Today on the Slanted Lens we are shooting in a studio in downtown Los Angeles. We have beautiful Cynthia Chavez on our set and we will be exploring advanced lighting setups. Combining a single Dynalite strobe head with a Photoflex silver P22 reflector and a $15.00 dollar mirror from Home Depot we can make a single strobe head look like several heads on set. This is a look at advanced lighting with a single head. I hope you will find this advanced look at a single light setup helpful. It's important to remember that hard light from mirrors and silver reflectors becomes almost as powerful as the main light source and can create multiple light sources on set. A 15 dollar mirror from Home depot is a great investment. You can modify them much like a regular light with flags and scrims and even diffusion. Keep those cameras rollin and keep on clickn'.</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Asal kita menguasai konsep 4 fungsi lighting tadi, kita bisa menggunakan lampu sebanyak kita mau. Coba tonton video berikut. Sekali lagi, jangan terpaku pada peralatan, tapi perhatikanlah fungsi dan dampak dari masing-masing sumber cahaya.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('dRgu84ZVYB0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/dRgu84ZVYB0?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/dRgu84ZVYB0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dRgu84ZVYB0" id="dRgu84ZVYB0" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Using Zones: Ep 111 Exploring Photography with Mark Wallace: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.adorama.com

Adorama Photography TV presents Exploring Photography with Mark Wallace. In this episode, Mark teaches you how to get six different looks from one lighting setup using zones.

You can use zones with both speedlights and studio strobes to control lighting groups independently. Mark will be using PocketWizard triggers to control his zones.

AdoramaTV features talented hosts including: Mark Wallace, Gavin Hoey, Joe McNally, Joe DiMaggio, Tamara Lackey, Bryan Peterson, and Rich Harrington.

Featured items from this episode
http://adr.ma/explore011a

AdoramaTV related episodes
http://adrma/explore011b

To learn more from the Adorama Learning Center
http://adr.ma/explore011c

Related Products at Adorama

Nikon D3S (only available used)

Nikon 70-200mm f/2.8G
http://www.adorama.com/NK70200AF2U.html

Profoto D1 1000 Watt Second Air
http://www.adorama.com/PP901025.html

Profoto D1 500 Watt Second Air
http://www.adorama.com/PP901024.html

Profoto Softbox 2'x3'
http://www.adorama.com/PP505702.html

Profoto White Softlight Reflector (beauty dish)
http://www.adorama.com/PP505507.html

Profoto Zoom Reflector 2
http://www.adorama.com/PP505517.html

Benro A2690TBH1 Travel Angel Aluminum Tripod
http://www.adorama.com/BEA2690TBH1.html

Profoto 5 Degree Honeycomb Grid
http://www.adorama.com/PP505571.html

PocketWizard Plus III Transceiver
http://www.adorama.com/PWP3T2.html

Foamcore White and Black Panels (homemade)

If you have questions, share them with us at: adotv@adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<h2>On Location</h2>

<p>Memotret dalam studio relatif lebih mudah, karena semua faktor bisa kita kendalikan. Yang lebih menantang adalah sesi foto di luar ruangan (outdoor). Hasil fotonya juga lebih bagus, karena latar belakangnya lebih variatif.</p>

<p>Kita mulai dengan teknik dasar, bagaimana mengatur proporsi cahaya alami (ambient) dengan cahaya dari lampu (strobe). Konsep dasarnya tetap ada di <a href="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/teknik/exposure-dan-metering/">teknik metering</a> dan <a href="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/teknik/segitiga-exposure/">pengaturan segitiga exposure</a>. Karena kita menggunakan flash, ada beberapa konsep tambahan:</p>

<ul>
<li>ISO : mempengaruhi intensitas ambient <strong>dan</strong> strobe</li>
<li>Aperture : <strong>hanya</strong> mempengaruhi intensitas strobe</li>
<li>Shutter speed : <strong>hanya</strong> mempengaruhi intensitas ambient</li>
</ul>


<p>Konsep di atas hanya berlaku kalau kita menggunakan setting manual di kamera dan manual juga di flash. Serba manual ini memudahkan kita untuk memahami cara kerjanya. Kalau nanti sudah paham, barulah kita gunakan mode otomatis (Aperture Priority dan TTL Flash) untuk mempercepat proses.</p>

<p>Pengaruh shutter speed terhadap ambient bisa dibaca <a href="http://strobist.blogspot.com/2007/09/lighting-102-33-balancing-flashambient.html">di sini</a>.</p>

<p>Dengan konsep di atas, berarti kita bisa mengatur intensitas ambient dan strobe secara terpisah. Kita bisa buat ambient gelap dan subjek (yang diterangi strobe) terang, atau sebaliknya. Variasi dalam rasio ambient-strobe ini bisa membuat foto kita lebih <em>punchy</em>. Kalau tidak percaya, bisa lihat contohnya <a href="http://strobist.blogspot.com/2006/03/lighting-101-balancing-flash-and.html">di sini</a>. Proses berpikir dalam mengatur rasio bisa dibaca <a href="http://neilvn.com/tangents/zones-of-light/">di sini</a>.</p>

<p>Setelah paham konsepnya, kita lihat aplikasinya.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('dTrS-0v-BLg');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/dTrS-0v-BLg?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/dTrS-0v-BLg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dTrS-0v-BLg" id="dTrS-0v-BLg" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Balancing Strobes with a Setting Sun: A Lighting Tutorial!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Sign up at http://theslantedlens.com for free video lighting tutorials & gear giveaways ***

Balancing Strobe Lights during Sunset: A Photo Lighting Tutorial! 
By Jay P. Morgan

"They say you shouldn't judge a book by a cover, but everyone of us who buys a book spends a few seconds looking at the title and the cover.  Not only that, publishers know that readers also flip the book over and look at the picture of the author.  That's why more and more authors and publishers are viewing the author photo as a marketing opportunity.  The author photo is just another opportunity to tell a story.  An author who takes a simple portrait is telling a story, but it's probably something like, "There is a reason this guy isn't a model."
Today's photo shoot is for Robert L. Harding.  Robert has written a Thriller called, Death of the Wayang, set in Indonesia, and we wanted to show something strong and action-oriented in the photo.  Robert likes airplane and is a student pilot.  We had an opportunity to shoot at historic Santa Paula airport surrounded by beautiful scenery, a number of vintage aircraft, including this Steerman Biplane, and framed by a gorgeous California sunset.  This lesson shows how we balanced our strobes with a setting sun to get an interesting Author Portrait.
Keep those cameras rolling, and keep on click'n! 
http://www.kesslercrane.com/
http://www.tamron-usa.com/
http://www.dynalite.com/
http://www.photoflex.com/
http://www.rosco.com/us/index.cfm
http://www.azdencorp.com
http://www.glidecam.com/
http://triplescoopmusic.com
http://theslantedlens.com/</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Perhatikan mulai menit ke 4:00. Fotografer mengurangi shutter speed seiring dengan semakin gelapnya kondisi ambient. Lihat info shutter speed dan jam pemotretan di keterangan foto. Perhatikan bahwa aperture dan ISO tidak berubah, sehingga intensitas strobe tidak berubah. Tahu dari mana bahwa strobe tidak berubah? Lihat dahi subjek yang diterangi oleh strobe. Tingkat terangnya tidak berubah walaupun shutter speed turun terus.</p>

<p>Amati juga bahwa intensitas ambient (terlihat dari latar belakang langit) juga tidak berubah walaupun hari semakin senja. Ini dimungkinkan karena fotografer mengkompensasi semakin gelapnya langit dengan shutter speed yang semakin lambat.</p>

<p>Selanjutnya, lihat video berikut</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('JuK_erfYaW0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/JuK_erfYaW0?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/JuK_erfYaW0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JuK_erfYaW0" id="JuK_erfYaW0" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Natural Light & Strobes on Location: A Lighting Tutorial</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Sign up at http://theslantedlens.com for free video lighting tutorials & gear giveaways ***

Usingn Natural Lighting & Strobe Lights on Location: A Photo Lighting Tutorial
By Jay P. Morgan

In this Slanted Lens video we look at the process of combining natural light and strobes on location. It's hard to shoot video and stills on the same set-up unless you plan for it. We needed both a crane shot and stills from our Pioneer set-up. Using a Kessler Crane we shot the crane shot during the sweet light time at sunset and then used strobes as the light faded to get our still shots. Using my iphone app (Sun Seeker) I could see exactly where the sun was going to go down. The scene was orientated to use the sun as the key for the video and then as the sun faded two strobes were used to take the place of the sun for the still shots. Tricky process, but necessary these days as clients are asking for both stills and video on the same set-up. Keep those cameras rolling and keep on click'n! 

http://www.kesslercrane.com/
http://www.tamron-usa.com/
http://www.niksoftware.com
http://www.henselusa.com
http://ikancorp.com/
http://www.glidecam.com/
http://triplescoopmusic.com
http://theslantedlens.com/</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Selalu menggunakan prinsip yang sama. Pertama, fotografer menggunakan matahari sebagai key light. Karena posisi matahari tidak bisa digeser-geser, maka subjek dan kamera yang bergeser. Semakin sore, matahari semakin gelap, sehingga tidak kuat lagi mengambil peran sebagai key. Oleh karena itu, strobe disuruh menjadi key light dan matahari menjadi fill light. Matahari sore warnanya oranye, sedangkan strobe putih, gunakan gel untuk mewarnai strobe supaya sama-sama oranye. Kalau warnanya sudah sama, nanti bisa diputihkan lagi di Photoshop. Terakhir, tambahkan satu strobe lagi supaya karavan terlihat.</p>

<h2>Light Modifier</h2>

<p>Di video-video sebelumnya, kita melihat penggunaan berbagai <em>light modifier</em> seperti payung, softbox, dan sebagainya. Sebenarnya apa fungsi dari modifier tersebut?</p>

<p>Fungsi utamanya sebetulnya adalah untuk memperbesar ukuran sumber cahaya relatif terhadap subjek. Kalau hanya lampu saja, maka ukuran lampu lebih kecil dari wajah subjek, sehingga bayangannya <em>hard</em>. Dengan menggunakan softbox atau payung, ukurannya menjadi besar, sehingga bayangannya menjadi <em>soft</em>.</p>

<p>Selain modifier (softbox atau payung), perlu juga diperhatikan masalah jarak. Matahari adalah sumber cahaya yang besar, bahkan ukurannya lebih besar daripada bumi. Tapi karena jaraknya jauh, maka menjadi kecil kalau dibandingkan dengan wajah subjek. Demikian juga dengan modifier. Percuma kita pakai softbox sebesar gajah kalau ditaruh di jarak 50 meter dari subjeknya.</p>

<p>Seperti apa perbedaan antara <em>hard</em> dan <em>soft</em>, bisa disimak di penjelasan Om Joe McNally berikut</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('vIsw495HtSI');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/vIsw495HtSI?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/vIsw495HtSI/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vIsw495HtSI" id="vIsw495HtSI" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Comparing Sizes: Small Flash Ep 106: Photo on the Go with Joe McNally: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.adorama.com

Adorama Photography TV Presents Photo on the Go with Joe McNally.  Joe is back in the jungles of Saint Lucia of the Eastern Caribbean with one of the island's lovely singers, Claudette.  

Once again, Claudette will be the subject of Joe's photography as he continues his experiment of different light sources. Using only small flash this time, Joe will test straight flash, off-camera straight flash, and through softboxes. Watch to see how they compare and contrast to each other.

AdoramaTV features talented hosts including: Mark Wallace, Gavin Hoey, Joe McNally, Joe DiMaggio, Tamara Lackey, Bryan Peterson, Rich Harrington

Related Products

Featured items from this episode
http://adr.ma/photog006c

AdoramaTV related episodes
http://adr.ma/photog006b

Learn More from the Adorama Learning Center
http://adr.ma/photog006a

Nikon D800E
http://www.adorama.com/INKD800E.html

Nikon 24-70 f/2.8
http://www.adorama.com/NK2470AFSU.html

Nikon 85 f/1.4
http://www.adorama.com/NK8514AFGU.html

Lumiquest III
http://www.adorama.com/LQSB3.html

Lumiquest Ltp
http://www.adorama.com/LQSBLTP.html

Lastolite 24" Joe McNally Ezybox
http://www.adorama.com/LSLS2462JM.html

Lastolite 32" Joe McNally Trigrip
http://www.adorama.com/LSLR3996JM.html

Avenger C-Stand Kit
http://www.adorama.com/AEA2030DK.html

If you have questions, share them with us at: adotv@adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Softbox ukurannya bermacam-macam, ada yang besar dan ada yang kecil. Apa bedanya? Simak penjelasan teorinya dari Om Jay P. Morgan berikut</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('gVy2nwoataM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/gVy2nwoataM?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/gVy2nwoataM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gVy2nwoataM" id="gVy2nwoataM" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Soft Boxes 101: A Lighting Lesson</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Sign up at http://theslantedlens.com for free video lighting tutorials & gear giveaways ***

Soft Boxes 101: A Lighting Lesson 
By Jay P. Morgan.

This Video is all about Soft Boxes. There are many misconceptions about what Soft Boxes do and how to use them. This is the scientific look at the area of coverage and light quality of the different sizes of Soft Boxes. Using this knowledge you will find it easier to decide which size Box to use to achieve your desired lighting result.  After this lesson you should know what size of Soft Box to buy and the basics of how to use it. Thanks to Photoflex http://www.photoflex.com/  for providing the Boxes for this test. There is much to learn on this subject so we will visit it again. Keep on click'n! Jay P. Morgan
http://theslantedlens.com/
http://fb.com/theslantedlens1
http://kesslercrane.com
http://henselusa.com
http://photoflex.com/</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Lanjutkan dengan contoh penerapannya</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('hmqDGCSDy0s');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/hmqDGCSDy0s?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/hmqDGCSDy0s/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmqDGCSDy0s" id="hmqDGCSDy0s" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Soft Boxes Applied: A lighting Lesson</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >** Sign up at http://theslantedlens.com for free video lighting tutorials & gear giveaways ***

Soft Boxes Applied: A Lighting Lesson 
By Jay P. Morgan

This Video is part two in a three part series about softboxes. It's showing how to create a simple three light set up to shoot a model. Part two shows how to apply the science of part one to a real life situation. The art of creating light is a language all its own. The language of light is the emotion that light creates in the viewer. Its not enough to know the science of using a soft box, you must understand how light effects people. This part introduces the idea that light is a language and it can cause different emotions in the viewer. Thanks to Photoflex http://www.photoflex.com  for providing the boxes for this demonstration. This is just an introduction to the idea that light causes emotion. We will talk about this often. The Language of Light. Keep on click'n!

http://theslantedlens.com
http://www.facebook.com/theslantedlens1
http://www.kesslercrane.com
http://henselusa.com
http://www.photoflex.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Payung sama dengan softbox, gunanya untuk memperbesar ukuran sumber cahaya.</p>

<blockquote><p>Apa bedanya softbox dan payung?</p></blockquote>

<p>Tonton penjelasan dari Om Mark Wallace</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('pyJ3YRMnqto');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/pyJ3YRMnqto?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/pyJ3YRMnqto/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pyJ3YRMnqto" id="pyJ3YRMnqto" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Light Modifiers: Ep 240: Digital Photography 1 on 1: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. This week Mark talks about the difference between an umbrella and a softbox. Learn how your light modifier is affected by size, shape and control.

Products used in this video:

Dynalite 40" Compact Umbrella, White / Black
http://www.adorama.com/DN4401B.html

Sekonic L-758DR DigitalMaster, Programmable Digital Flash & Ambient Exposure Meter
http://www.adorama.com/SKL758DR.html

Profoto Silver Umbrella 42" #100616 / 505-605 
http://www.adorama.com/PP505605.html

Profoto D1 500 Watt Second Air Monolight Flash with Built-in Reflector & Power Cable, Coated Flash Tube
http://www.adorama.com/PP901024.html

Flashpoint II 24" x 36", 60cm x 91cm, Softbox for all Model II Monolights
http://www.adorama.com/FP2SB2436.html

Profoto 50° Magnum Reflector #100624 / 505-504
http://www.adorama.com/PP505504.html

Profoto D1 500 Watt Second Air Monolight Flash with Built-in Reflector & Power Cable, Coated Flash Tube
http://www.adorama.com/PP901024.html
 
Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Selain modifier yang pakai lampu seperti softbox dan payung, ada juga modifier tanpa lampu. Contohnya reflektor (pemantul cahaya) dan scrim/diffuser (untuk menghalangi atau menyebarkan cahaya)</p>

<p>Contoh penggunaan scrim untuk menyebarkan cahaya didemonstrasikan oleh om Joe McNally di video ini</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('eR7wXxvrRMA');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/eR7wXxvrRMA?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/eR7wXxvrRMA/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eR7wXxvrRMA" id="eR7wXxvrRMA" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Managing Hard Sunlight, On-Location Ep 108: Photo on the Go with Joe McNally: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.adorama.com

Adorama Photography TV Presents Photo on the Go with Joe McNally.  Join Joe in Guanajuato, Mexico as he demonstrates the strategies of managing hard sunlight.

In a location that has a lot of sunlight it can be hard to find a good spot that will avoid hard shadows on your subject.  In this episode, Joe will use different techniques and equipment that will help diffuse the lighting, creating a much softer photograph.

AdoramaTV features talented hosts including: Mark Wallace, Gavin Hoey, Joe McNally, Joe DiMaggio, Tamara Lackey, Bryan Peterson, Rich Harrington

Related Products

Featured items from this episode
http://adr.ma/photogo08c

AdoramaTV related episodes
http://adr.ma/photogo08b

Learn More from the Adorama Learning Center
http://adr.ma/photogo08a

Nikon D800
http://www.adorama.com/INKD800.html

Nikon 85 f/1.8
http://www.adorama.com/NK8518U.html

Manfrotto Air Cushioned Light Stand
http://www.adorama.com/BG1005BAC.html

Manfrotto Justin Clamp
http://www.adorama.com/BG175F.html

Frio Cold Shoe Adapter
http://www.adorama.com/LTFRIO.html

Nikon SB-910 Speedlight
http://www.adorama.com/NKSB910AFU.html

Lastolite Trigrip Holder
http://www.adorama.com/LSTGHWFB.html

Lastolite Joe McNally 32" Trigrip
http://www.adorama.com/LSLR3996JM.html

Lastolite Ezybox Speed-Lite
http://www.adorama.com/LSEZBSL.html

Kacey Pole Adapter
http://www.adorama.com/LTKPA.html

Lastolite Trigrip Holder with Flash Bracket
http://www.adorama.com/LSTGHWFB.html

Lastolite Joe McNally 32" Trigrip Reflector Kit
http://www.adorama.com/LSLR3996JM.html

If you have questions, share them with us at: adotv@adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Di bagian kedua, scrim digunakan untuk menghalangi cahaya</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('AOhscpY-wQo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/AOhscpY-wQo?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/AOhscpY-wQo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AOhscpY-wQo" id="AOhscpY-wQo" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Managing Hard Sunlight, Part II Ep 109: Photo on the Go with Joe McNally: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.adorama.com

Adorama Photography TV Presents Photo on the Go with Joe McNally.  Join Joe in Guanajuato, Mexico as he continues his experiments with different strategies of managing hard sunlight.

In a location that has a lot of sunlight it can be hard to find a good spot that will avoid hard shadows on your subject.  In this episode, Joe will use different techniques and equipment that will help diffuse the lighting, creating a much softer photograph.

AdoramaTV features talented hosts including: Mark Wallace, Gavin Hoey, Joe McNally, Joe DiMaggio, Tamara Lackey, Bryan Peterson, Rich Harrington

Related Products

Nikon D800
http://www.adorama.com/INKD800.html

Nikon 85 f/1.8
http://www.adorama.com/NK8518U.html

Manfrotto Air Cushioned Light Stand
http://www.adorama.com/BG1005BAC.html

Manfrotto Justin Clamp
http://www.adorama.com/BG175F.html

Frio Cold Shoe Adapter
http://www.adorama.com/LTFRIO.html

Nikon SB-910 Speedlight
http://www.adorama.com/NKSB910AFU.html

Lastolite Trigrip Holder
http://www.adorama.com/LSTGHWFB.html

Lastolite Joe McNally 32" Trigrip
http://www.adorama.com/LSLR3996JM.html

Lastolite Ezybox Speed-Lite
http://www.adorama.com/LSEZBSL.html

Kacey Pole Adapter
http://www.adorama.com/LTKPA.html



If you have questions, share them with us at: adotv@adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Reflektor berfungsi untuk memantulkan cahaya. Bisa cahaya dari strobe ataupun cahaya matahari. Biasanya tersedia dalam format 5 in 1, punya 5 sisi dalam 1 unit:</p>

<ul>
<li>hitam : untuk menghalangi cahaya (seperti scrim-nya Om Joe)</li>
<li>translucent/semi-transparan : untuk menyebarkan cahaya (seperti scrim-nya Om Joe)</li>
<li>putih : untuk memantulkan cahaya</li>
<li>silver : memantulkan cahaya lebih banyak daripada putih</li>
<li>gold : memantulkan cahaya berwarna emas, seperti matahari sore</li>
</ul>


<p>Contoh pemakaiannya bisa dilihat di sini</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('QT2XTvuyQms');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QT2XTvuyQms?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/QT2XTvuyQms/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QT2XTvuyQms" id="QT2XTvuyQms" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Creating Professional Photography w/ $30 Reflectors - Photography Lighting Tutorial</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Learn more about Natural Light Portrait Photography Here: 

http://slrlounge.com/couples-photography

About a month ago, we took on the challenge of shooting an entire fashion shoot with just an iPhone and a couple $30 reflectors as a follow up video to the FStoppers iPhone Fashion Shoot. The SLR Lounge iPhone Photo Shoot has gotten a lot of attention and we thought it was time for a follow up video.

So, in this follow up video, we will be showing you guys the exact reflector lighting techniques that we used to pull off every shot that we took in the SLR Lounge iPhone Photo Shoot.

However, we will be using a legit camera this time. This time we will be using our 5D Mark II along with a 50mm 1.4 Prime Lens. But, trust me that you can pretty much get these exact same shots with virtually any DSLR body with a 50mm 1.4 Prime Lens attached. Below the video, we have listed out all of the equipment and software used to create these shots. So be sure to check that out as well.

Enjoy, and as always, let us know what you think!</div>
</div>

</p>

<p><blockquote><p>John Loengard, the picture editor at Life, always used to tell me, ”If you want something to look interesting, don&rsquo;t light all of it.</p><footer><strong>Joe McNally</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Artinya, kita harus membatasi bagian yang terkena cahaya supaya fotonya lebih menarik. Salah satu cara membatasi cahaya adalah menggunakan grid.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('g5zxYDSQPNo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/g5zxYDSQPNo?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/g5zxYDSQPNo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g5zxYDSQPNo" id="g5zxYDSQPNo" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Shooting with Grids: Ep 238: Digital Photography 1 on 1</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. In this episode Mark Wallace demonstrates the use of grids in the studio. Mark shows you how grids help to restrict the light falling on the subject.
 
Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Jangan buru-buru beli grid mahal-mahal. Kita bisa bikin sendiri <a href="http://strobist.blogspot.com/2006/10/free-and-so-easy-diy-grid-spots-for.html">dari kardus</a>, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/71265688@N00/sets/72157594358068593/show/">coroplast</a>, atau <a href="http://lightingmods.blogspot.com/2007/06/diy-black-straws-snoot-grid-part-1.html">dari sedotan bekas</a>.</p>

<p>Masih banyak lagi jenis-jenis modifier lain seperti didemokan Om Mark Wallace</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('8sKK_lvQiVA');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/8sKK_lvQiVA?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/8sKK_lvQiVA/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8sKK_lvQiVA" id="8sKK_lvQiVA" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Small Studio Flash Tips: Ep 208: Digital Photography 1 on 1: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. In this week's episode Mark responds to a couple's question about their home studio and how best to use speedlights in a small space. Join Mark as he walks you through the basics of shooting with speedlights in a 12' x 12' studio.

For related articles and videos, and to buy the products used in this video, go here:  http://www.adorama.com/alc/article/Small-Studio-Flash-Tips-AdoramaTV

Watch Episode 17: Sync Speed:
http://youtu.be/fOayN2U1xZg

Watch Episode 54: Speedlights vs. Studio Strobes:
http://youtu.be/s0ZmscWEc1c

Products used in this episode: 
Nikon D7000 Digital SLR Camera Body, 16.2 Megapixel, 1080HD Movie, U.S.A. Warranty http://www.adorama.com/INKD7000.html
Nikon 18mm - 55mm f/3.5-5.6G AF-S DX (VR) Vibration Reduction Wide Angle Autofocus Zoom Lens, U.S.A. Warranty http://www.adorama.com/NK1855VRU.html
Canon Speedlite 580EX II, Shoe Mount Flash with Guide Number of 190 Feet / 58m at ISO 100, U.S.A. Warranty http://www.adorama.com/CA580EX2U.html
Nikon SU-800 Replacement Wireless Speedlight Commander http://www.adorama.com/NKSU800.html
Nikon SB-700 TTL AF Shoe Mount Speedlight http://www.adorama.com/NKSB700AFU.html
Canon EOS Rebel T3i Digital SLR Camera, 18 Megapixels, Full HD Movie Mode, Canon EF-S 18-55mm f/3.5-5.6 IS II Lens http://www.adorama.com/ICAT3IK.html
Westcott 32" White Satin Umbrella with Removable Black Cover http://www.adorama.com/WEU32SBC.html
HonlPhoto 8" Regular Speed Snoot http://www.adorama.com/FAHSN.html
Gary Fong Lightsphere Collapsible - Half Cloud http://www.adorama.com/GALSCOL.html
Interfit Photographic Umbrella Holder with Hotshoe Adapter http://www.adorama.com/PASTR117.html

Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<h2>Warna</h2>

<p>Flash bisa diwarnai dengan plastik berwarna yang disebut dengan istilah <code>gel</code>. Tujuannya macam-macam, diantaranya:</p>

<ul>
<li>supaya sama dengan ambient. Kalau sudah sama, gampang dinetralisir di Photoshop. Jauh lebih mudah menetralisir cahaya hijau yang seragam, daripada cahaya hijau dari kiri dan putih dari kanan.</li>
<li>untuk menimbulkan efek dramatis</li>
</ul>


<p>Yang perlu diperhatikan, begitu kita bermain-main dengan warna, kita harus mematikan fitur <code>Auto White Balance</code> di kamera. Kita harus mengatur sendiri <code>White Balance</code> supaya warnanya sesuai dengan yang seharusnya, tidak diatur otomatis oleh kamera.</p>

<p>Untuk lebih jelasnya, simak penjelasan Om Mark Wallace</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('LiPL73mLeJ8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/LiPL73mLeJ8?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/LiPL73mLeJ8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LiPL73mLeJ8" id="LiPL73mLeJ8" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Digital Photography 1 on 1: Episode 13: White Balance: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Adorama Photography TV presents: In this episode Mark Wallace discusses how different sources of light affect the colors of your photographs. Mark explains color temperature and white balance, and demonstrates how you can get the most accurate color in your images.

Visit http://www.adorama.com/alc/category/AdoramaTV for more videos!

For links to articles, videos and products related to this video, go to http://www.adorama.com/alc/article/White-Balance-AdoramaTV

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Biasanya fotografer akan menggunakan kertas putih atau abu-abu sebagai patokan warna, sehingga nanti mudah melakukan koreksi di Photoshop. Kertas ini disebut dengan <code>white card</code> atau <code>grey card</code>. Bagaimana menggunakannya? Tonton penjelasan dari Om Mark</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('H5rW74-zCQ0');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/H5rW74-zCQ0?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/H5rW74-zCQ0/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H5rW74-zCQ0" id="H5rW74-zCQ0" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Using the ColorChecker Passport: Ep 209: Digital Photography 1 on 1: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. In this week's episode Mark answers a question regarding color calibration and correction. Join Mark in the studio as he demonstrates the use of the ColorChecker Passport to achieve accurate and consistent color.

Watch Episode 13: White Balance:
http://youtu.be/LiPL73mLeJ8

Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Setelah paham urusan <code>white balance</code>, kita simak penerapannya oleh Om Joe McNally, bagian pertama</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('ntoRpQCY60U');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ntoRpQCY60U?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/ntoRpQCY60U/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ntoRpQCY60U" id="ntoRpQCY60U" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Joe McNally - Control of Color (1/2)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >"The best photographs move you—emotionally, intellectually, spiritually. There's almost a visceral reaction to a really striking photograph that communicates on all those levels."

Joe McNally has been described as "perhaps the most versatile photojournalist working today," a distinction earned for his ability to capture compelling images in locations as diverse as an operating room, the top of the Empire State Building and the cockpit of a jet aircraft. Noted for his technical mastery, what makes him unique is his ability to create and imaginatively render "the big idea"—the unique or startling concept that frames a single image or a long-term project.

He has been published in virtually every major magazine, including Life, Newsweek, Time and Sports Illustrated (where he was a contract photographer for six years) and is a recipient of the Alfred Eisenstadt Award for outstanding magazine photography.

To see more of Joe's work visit his website at www.joemcnally.com.</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>dan bagian kedua</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('W3azZ0wIXpo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/W3azZ0wIXpo?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/W3azZ0wIXpo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W3azZ0wIXpo" id="W3azZ0wIXpo" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Joe McNally - Control of Color (2/2)</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >"The best photographs move you—emotionally, intellectually, spiritually. There's almost a visceral reaction to a really striking photograph that communicates on all those levels."

Joe McNally has been described as "perhaps the most versatile photojournalist working today," a distinction earned for his ability to capture compelling images in locations as diverse as an operating room, the top of the Empire State Building and the cockpit of a jet aircraft. Noted for his technical mastery, what makes him unique is his ability to create and imaginatively render "the big idea"—the unique or startling concept that frames a single image or a long-term project.

He has been published in virtually every major magazine, including Life, Newsweek, Time and Sports Illustrated (where he was a contract photographer for six years) and is a recipient of the Alfred Eisenstadt Award for outstanding magazine photography.

To see more of Joe's work visit his website at www.joemcnally.com.</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Kalau mau lebih ekstrim, simak penggunaan gel oleh Om Bryan Peterson</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('rK1rlkSKkD8');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/rK1rlkSKkD8?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/rK1rlkSKkD8/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rK1rlkSKkD8" id="rK1rlkSKkD8" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Two Flashes, Two Gels Ep 316: You Keep Shooting with Bryan Peterson: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.adorama.com

AdoramaTV Presents You Keep Shooting with Bryan Peterson. In this episode, Bryan will show you how to shoot a creative photo using two flashes and two gels.

Join Bryan as he takes you step by step through the process of shooting a subject in creative lighting to produce a unique CD cover or poster.  For something a little different, try using additional lighting and colored gels.

AdoramaTV features talented hosts including: Mark Wallace, Gavin Hoey, Joe McNally, Joe DiMaggio, Tamara Lackey, Bryan Peterson, and Rich Harrington.

Related Products

Featured items from this episode
http://adr.ma/keepshooting016a

AdoramaTV related episodes
http://adr.ma/keepshooting016b

To learn more from the Adorama Learning Center
http://adr.ma/keepshooting016c

Understanding Flash Photography
http://www.adorama.com/BKUFP.html

Understanding Photography Field Guide by Bryan Peterson
http://www.adorama.com/BKUPFG.html

Nikon D800 Digital SLR Camera
http://www.adorama.com/INKD800.html

Nikon SB-900 TTL AF Shoe Mount Speedlight
http://www.adorama.com/NKSB900AFR.html

Nikon SB-910 TTL AF Shoe Mount Speedlight
http://www.adorama.com/NKSB910AFU.html

Flashpoint Flash Diffuser for the Nikon SB 900 and SB 910 Flashes
http://www.adorama.com/FAFD80.html

Nikon SJ-3 Color Filter Set for SB-910 and SB-900 Speedlights
http://www.adorama.com/NKSJ3.html

Sto-Fen Gold Colored Omni-Bounce for the Nikon SB 900 and SB 910
http://www.adorama.com/SFOC900GL.html


If you have questions, share them with us at: adotv@adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<h2>Intensitas</h2>

<p>Seperti kita lihat di video-video di atas, intinya adalah bermain dengan kombinasi dan rasio terang-gelap. Untuk itu, kita harus mahir mengatur intensitas cahaya baik di subjek maupun di lingkungan sekitarnya. Pertama, kita kuasai dulu pengaturan power di strobe</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('E-ro-ST3iuo');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/E-ro-ST3iuo?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/E-ro-ST3iuo/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E-ro-ST3iuo" id="E-ro-ST3iuo" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Understanding Watt-Seconds: Ep 239: DIgital Photography 1 on 1</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. What are watt-seconds? Mark Wallace takes several minutes to explain watt-seconds, how they influence the amount of light emitted by a flash, and what other factors may effect light intensity. Come along for an enlightening look into power and light in the photo studio.

Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com

Related Products: 

Profoto D1 500 Watt Second Air Monolight Flash with Built-in Reflector & Power Cable, Coated Flash Tube: http://www.adorama.com/PP901024.html

Flashpoint II 1220A Monolight, 600 Watt Second Strobe: http://www.adorama.com/FP1220A.html

Profoto D1 1000 Watt Second Air Monolight Flash with Built-in Reflector & Power Cable, Coated Flash Tube http://www.adorama.com/PP901025.html

Flashpoint 2420 Monolight, 1200 Watt Second Fan Cooled Strobe, 120 volt: http://www.adorama.com/FP2420.html

Profoto Pro-8a 1200 Air Power Pack, 1200 Watt Second Flash Generator: http://www.adorama.com/PP701081.html

Sekonic L-758DR DigitalMaster, Programmable Digital Flash & Ambient Exposure Meter: http://www.adorama.com/SKL758DR.html

Profoto Zoom Reflector 2 - Accepts Profoto Grids, No Gridholder Needed: http://www.adorama.com/PP505517.html

Profoto Silver Umbrella 42": http://www.adorama.com/PP505605.html</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Untuk flash kecil (speedlight), silahkan baca user manual merek dan tipe masing-masing.</p>

<p>Setelah bisa mengatur power, kita harus paham konsep Inverse Square Law. Intinya, bagaimana hubungan antara jarak lampu-subjek-latar terhadap <em>fall off</em>, perbedaan intensitas cahaya antara subjek dan latarnya. Konsepnya bisa ditonton di sini</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('f5BIvSBjvLg');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/f5BIvSBjvLg?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/f5BIvSBjvLg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f5BIvSBjvLg" id="f5BIvSBjvLg" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Digital Photography 1 on 1: Episode 59: Inverse Square Law: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. In this week's episode Mark Wallace explains the Inverse Square law and how it applies to photography.

For related articles and videos on exposure and photographic calculations, go here: http://www.adorama.com/alc/article/Inverse-Square-Law-AdoramaTV

Buy a Cameron Octobox Strobist Kit with Cameron 8' Light Stand
at Adorama.com
http://www.adorama.com/FAA0SK.html


Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Dengan memahami konsep Inverse Square Law, kita bisa mengatur agar:</p>

<ul>
<li>subjek dan latar sama terang</li>
<li>subjek terang, latar gelap</li>
</ul>


<p>hanya dengan mengubah jarak lampu &mdash;> subjek &mdash;> latar.</p>

<h2>Durasi Cahaya</h2>

<p>Berdasarkan lama menyala, sumber cahaya bisa dibagi dua:</p>

<ul>
<li>continuous : menyala terus selama shutter terbuka. Contohnya matahari, lampu rumah.</li>
<li>flash/instant : menyala sesaat saja. Contohnya flash, monolight</li>
</ul>


<p>Perbedaan antara keduanya bisa ditonton di sini</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('4QaCI_SUc5c');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/4QaCI_SUc5c?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/4QaCI_SUc5c/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4QaCI_SUc5c" id="4QaCI_SUc5c" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Constant Light Versus Flash Light: Ep 234: Digital Photography 1 on 1: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >AdoramaTV Presents Digital Photography One on One. In this episode Mark walks through the differences between using constant light and light from a flash. Join Mark in the studio for a hands-on demonstration that shows how constant light produces different results than light coming from a flash.

For related articles and videos, and to learn more about products mentioned in this video, go here: http://www.adorama.com/alc/article/Constant-Light-Versus-Flash-Light-Adorama-TV
 
Visit http://www.adorama.com/learn for more photography videos!

Send your questions to: AskMark@Adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Sumber cahaya instan (flash) hanya menyala sebentar saja. Sekitar 1/1000 detik atau lebih cepat. Oleh karena itu, setting shutter speed di kamera tidak mempengaruhi jumlah cahaya yang direkam sensor. Walaupun demikian, kita tidak bisa menggunakan shutter speed yang terlalu tinggi, karena dibatasi oleh sync-speed. Apa itu sync-speed? Saksikan penjelasan dari Om Mark Wallace</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('fOayN2U1xZg');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/fOayN2U1xZg?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/fOayN2U1xZg/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fOayN2U1xZg" id="fOayN2U1xZg" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Digital Photography 1 on 1: Episode 17: Sync Speed: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Adorama Photography TV presents: In this episode Mark talks about the basics of sync speed and teaches how to use sync speed properly. 

Go here for information about products used in this video, and for related articles and videos at the Adorama Learning Center: http://www.adorama.com/alc/article/Flash-Sync-Speed-AdoramaTV

Visit http://www.adorama.com/alc/category/AdoramaTV for more photography videos!</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Karena durasi yang singkat, seperti halnya shutter speed, flash juga memiliki kemampuan membekukan gerakan. Semakin singkat durasi flash, semakin cepat gerakan yang bisa dibekukan. Durasi flash diukur dalam satuan <code>t5</code> (waktu yang dibutuhkan flash sampai nyalanya tinggal 50%) dan <code>t1</code> (waktu yang dibutuhkan flash sampai cahayanya tinggal 10%). Teori tentang durasi flash bisa dibaca <a href="http://strobist.blogspot.com/2010/06/rise-and-fall-of-machines-understanding.html">di sini</a>. Sedangkan contoh aplikasinya didemokan oleh Om Sam McGuire di sini</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('zLGDxKDE05I');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/zLGDxKDE05I?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/zLGDxKDE05I/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zLGDxKDE05I" id="zLGDxKDE05I" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">How To: Flash Duration - Skateboarding Photographer Sam McGuire- In Focus</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Tune in every Monday to learn firsthand how to film, edit and shoot like the pros, from your favorite videographers and photographers in skateboarding!


Subscribe to Ride:
http://www.youtube.com/subscription_center?add_user=ridechannel
http://facebook.com/ridechannel
http://twitter.com/ridechannel
instagram @ridechannel</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Pemanfaatan durasi flash untuk membekukan gerakan juga bisa dilihat di demo berikut</p>

<iframe src="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com//player.vimeo.com/video/32792549?portrait=0" width="400" height="225" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/32792549">Bron vs Profoto</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/bronimaginggroup">Hasselblad Bron Inc.</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>

<p>Dengan mengkombinasikan durasi shutter speed dan durasi flash, kita bisa membuat berbagai efek menarik seperti yang dicontohkan Om Bryan Peterson</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('Dgnci8MH4sE');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Dgnci8MH4sE?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/Dgnci8MH4sE/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dgnci8MH4sE" id="Dgnci8MH4sE" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Second and Rear Curtain Sync: You Keep Shooting with Bryan Peterson: Adorama Photography TV</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >http://www.adorama.com

Adorama Photography TV Presents, You Keep Shooting with Bryan Peterson. Join Bryan as he explores creative techniques that will elevate your photography skills. Watch as he describes two approaches to photographing subjects in low light with an electronic flash.

Knowing about your camera's shutter is very important when shooting in low light. A slower shutter speed will allow more movement in your photograph. In this episode, Bryan will explain how and when it is appropriate to use electronic flashes during low-lighting conditions.

AdoramaTV features talented hosts including: Mark Wallace, Gavin Hoey, Joe McNally, Joe DiMaggio, Tamara Lackey, Bryan Peterson, and Rich Harrington.

Related Products:
Gel Kits
http://www.adorama.com/SearchSite/Default.aspx?searchinfo=gels

Understanding Flash Photography, by Bryan Peterson
http://www.adorama.com/BKUFP.html

Understanding Photography Field Guide, by Bryan Peterson
http://www.adorama.com/BKUPFG.html


If you have questions, share them with us at: adotv@adorama.com</div>
</div>

</p>

<h2>Permukaan</h2>

<p>Belajar lighting belum lengkap kalau belum memotret permukaan yang aneh-aneh, yaitu:</p>

<ul>
<li>tembus pandang. Misalnya gelas, botol, dan sejenisnya</li>
<li>memantulkan cahaya. Misalnya sendok, garpu, panci, dan logam lainnya</li>
<li>bertekstur. Misalnya kain, tembok, lukisan, dan lainnya</li>
</ul>


<p>Kita mulai dari permukaan tembus pandang. Silahkan tonton penjelasan Om Karl Taylor.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('IIm-SZHKOW4');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/IIm-SZHKOW4?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/IIm-SZHKOW4/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IIm-SZHKOW4" id="IIm-SZHKOW4" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Karl Taylor's Hi-End Product Shoot - Made Easy!</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >Watch this pro-level studio product photo-shoot right now!

http://www.karltaylorphotography.com/pro-photography

This type of shot is normally considered complex because of the interaction of light with liquid and glass. I run you through this studio bottle shoot step-by-step and reveal some professional tips for achieving this type of image.

http://www.karltaylorphotography.com/pro-photography</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Inti dari memotret botol dan gelas adalah menghilangkan tepi sumber cahaya yang terlalu tajam. Ini dilakukan dengan cara <code>diffusion</code>. Sumber cahaya dihalangi oleh bahan yang tembus cahaya tapi tidak bening. Kita bisa gunakan kertas kalkir yang tersedia di toko buku.</p>

<p>Selanjutnya, memotret logam oleh Pro Photo Life</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('KoY-cyxDMEk');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/KoY-cyxDMEk?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/KoY-cyxDMEk/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KoY-cyxDMEk" id="KoY-cyxDMEk" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Episode 15 , Photographing Shiny Metal and Reflections</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >A very important principle (the law of reflection) is applied to photographing shiny things in the studio. More info at prophotolife.com , do a search for episode 15.</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Dalam memotret benda mengkilap, kita justru harus memotret pantulan cahayanya. Prinsip yang digunakan ada di pelajaran IPA waktu SD, sudut datang cahaya = sudut pantul.</p>

<p>Berikutnya, memotret benda bertekstur.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('2CnAcWAO5bU');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2CnAcWAO5bU?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/2CnAcWAO5bU/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2CnAcWAO5bU" id="2CnAcWAO5bU" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">How to Photograph Texture</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >More tutorials @ http://learnmyshot.com .  Watch this photography tutorial to learn how to light your subject to emphasize on texture.</div>
</div>

</p>

<p>Ada dua pilihan dalam memotret benda bertekstur seperti kain:</p>

<ul>
<li>menonjolkan teksturnya. Misalnya memotret jeans.</li>
<li>menyembunyikan teksturnya. Misalnya memotret kemeja resmi.</li>
</ul>


<p>Untuk menonjolkan tekstur, gunakan cahaya dari samping. Sedangkan untuk menyembunyikan tekstur, gunakan cahaya lurus dari depan/atas. Ilustrasinya dijelaskan <a href="http://photography.tutsplus.com/articles/how-to-photograph-fabric-and-clothes--photo-12330">di artikel ini</a>.</p>

<h2>Kesimpulan</h2>

<p>Demikianlah berbagai teknik tentang penggunaan lighting. Tidak perlu galau dengan banyaknya video di atas, intinya hanyalah pemahaman terhadap konsep:</p>

<ul>
<li>rasio/proporsi intensitas antar beberapa sumber cahaya</li>
<li>sifat bayangan (hard atau soft), sering juga disebut dengan istilah <code>quality of light</code> di tutorial berbahasa Inggris</li>
<li>warna cahaya</li>
<li>durasi cahaya</li>
<li>karakteristik permukaan</li>
</ul>


<p>Dan penguasaan teknik kontrol cahaya:</p>

<ul>
<li>kontrol intensitas strobe dengan mengubah aperture, power lampu, dan jarak lampu-subjek-latar</li>
<li>kontrol intensitas ambient dengan mengubah shutter speed</li>
<li>kontrol sifat bayangan dengan mengubah ukuran sumber cahaya (menggunakan softbox atau payung)</li>
<li>kontrol tempat jatuhnya highlight/shadow dengan mengatur penempatan sumber cahaya dan menggunakan reflektor, grid, snoot, gobo</li>
<li>kontrol warna dengan gel dan setting white balance</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips Memotret dengan Handphone]]></title>
    <link href="http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/referensi/tips-memotret-dengan-handphone/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-31T09:36:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rana.endy.muhardin.com/referensi/tips-memotret-dengan-handphone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Smartphone jaman sekarang sudah bisa menghasilkan kualitas foto yang sangat baik. Ditambah lagi dengan adanya berbagai filter kreatif dan Instagram, sangat memudahkan kita untuk membuat dan mengekspresikan kreativitas kita.</p>

<p>Walaupun demikian, yang lebih penting adalah visi dan skill yang dimiliki pembuat foto, yang dirangkum dalam <a href="http://www.digitalinformationworld.com/2013/10/phone-tography-101-infographic-tips-and.html">infografis dari <code>Totally Rad</code></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
